Guide to the Warren Dwight Allen Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Warren Dwight Allen papers
1929-1957
SC0723
Allen, Warren Dwight, 1885-1964.
2 Linear feet
These papers pertain largely to his teaching career at Florida State University and Stanford University. The papers include his mimeographed texts on music and history that he used for classes at Florida State University School of Music; typescripts of papers and lectures, 1936-54 and undated; reprints and articles by Allen and others; correspondence, mostly pertaining to publication permissions, 1944-53, and his retirement from Stanford, 1950; and assorted clippings, programs, and other ephemera, 1929-55.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Warren Dwight Allen attended the University of California at Berkeley and was admitted to the American Guild of Organists in 1909. After two years of study in Paris and Berlin, he returned to the United States and taught at the College of the Pacific prior to his appointment in 1918 as the University Organist at Stanford, a post that he held until 1947. He received his A.B. degree in Philosophy from Stanford in1934 and then completed his Master of Arts degree in 1935 at U.C. Berkeley. In 1939 he received his Ph.D. degree from Columbia University in the fields of educational sociology and musicology. Allen played a pivotal role in the establishment of a Music Department at Stanford and was appointed Professor of Music and Education in 1941. He left Stanford in 1950 to teach at Florida State University.
Description of the Collection
These papers pertain largely to his teaching career at Florida State University and Stanford University. The papers include his mimeographed texts on music and history that he used for classes at Florida State University School of Music; typescripts of papers and lectures, 1936-54 and undated; reprints and articles by Allen and others; correspondence, mostly pertaining to publication permissions, 1944-53, and his retirement from Stanford, 1950; and assorted clippings, programs, and other ephemera, 1929-55.
Access Terms
Allen, Warren Dwight, 1885-1964.; Stanford University. Department of Music.; Music--Instruction and study.; Musicology.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Music and History: Volume 1 (To A.D. 900), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Music and History: Volume 3 (1601-1800), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Music and History in Five Great Cycles (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Music and History in Five Great Cycles, Volume Two, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Music and History: Since 1800 (1 of 2), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Music and History: Since 1800 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Music and History: The XIX Century, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A Bibliography of General Music Histories, typescript (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Music and Language, typescript (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Philosophies of Music History, corrected text of book published in 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Philosophies of Music History: Preface and Supplement to the 2nd Edition, typescript, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - “Arts and the Man,” presidential address to MTNA, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Address For Music And Arts Institute of San Francisco, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “Our Idioms of Musical Expression,” reprint, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Essays, 1940-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Lectures, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - “The Modern Cycle: Songs & Polyphony Under Henry VIII” – class materials and typescript text/lectures (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Music 348: 1801-1914 – typescript text/lectures (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - “Music and the Idea of Progress,” 1946 and "Music in Russia and the West," 1949 – reprints (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - “Music Amid World Revolutions,” typescript, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - “Philosophies of Music History,” typescript, 1939-1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Journal of Human Ecology: Miscellaneous Articles 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - “Music History in Climatic-Cultural Cycles” 1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - “Music History in Five Five-Hundred-Year Cycles” 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Publications of the Faculty and Theses Directed, Florida State University, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and newspaper clippings 1940-1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous recital announcements 1935-1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Pat Allen, Creative Writing class notes, poetry and stories, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Permissions for use of material in Allen's publications, 1944-1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Retirement letters 1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stanford Miscellany 1937-1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Victoria Music Festival 1929-1931 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Typescript papers and lectures, 1936-1953 and undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Typescript papers and lectures, 1939-1941 and undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, articles, etc., 1930-55 (Box 4, Folder 11)